Okay, boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's daf דף daf is
nun daled נ"ד, Nun Daled, 54. Is it nun daled נ"ד? Nun
Daled? No, it's nun hey נ"ה, Nun Hey, 55, as I was
saying. Today's daf דף daf is nun hey נ"ה, Nun Hey, and
we pick up on the Gemara גמרא Gemara right after the Mishnah
משנה. Mishnah. The Mishnah משנה Mishnah lists that zivchei זבחי... zivchei... so
this is going to be like going more quickly going through the
mishnayot משניות mishnayot about the different korbanot קרבנות korbanot and how they
were done. So it says that we're finishing up the kodshei kodashim
קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. So the rest after we did chatas חטאת
chatas and olah עולה, olah,
the other big categories: asham אשם, asham, the Mishnah משנה Mishnah mentioned
all the ashamot vadai אשמות ודאי ashamot vadai like, you know, ashamot
אשמות ashamot for a definite sin, and then the one case called
asham taluy אשם תלוי asham taluy when there's a question if you
did a type of a sin that you would bring a chatas
חטאת chatas for, plus zivchei shalmei tzibur זבחי שלמי ציבור, zivchei shalmei
tzibur, shelamim שלמים shelamim that are brought on behalf of the entire
community. Those—there really
is one thing that fits in that category, which is the shelamim
שלמים shelamim that are brought on Shavuot שבועות. Shavuot. And that's also
kodshei kodashim קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay, so therefore it's in the
north and it's the two that are four in terms of the
sides of the, you know, the corners of the mizbe'ach מזבח. mizbe'ach.
So let's take a look at the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, top of
nun hey נ"ה. Nun Hey. Minalan d'ba'i tzafon מנלן דבעי צפון? Minalan
d'ba'i tzafon? Where do we get this idea that you need north?
D'tani Rabba bar Rav Chanan kamei d'Rava דתני רבה בר רב חנן
קמיה דרבא, D'tani Rabba bar Rav Chanan kamei d'Rava, meaning specifically for
the... for the shalmei tzibur שלמי
ציבור. shalmei tzibur. Okay. V'asitem se'ir izim echad l'chatas ועשיתם שעיר עזים
אחד לחטאת, V'asitem se'ir izim echad l'chatas, and the end of the
pasuk פסוק pasuk is, what is it?
V'shnei kevasim b'nei shana l'zevach shelamim ושני כבשים בני שנה לזבח שלמים.
V'shnei kevasim b'nei shana l'zevach shelamim. Okay, so that's by the pasuk
פסוק pasuk by Shavuot שבועות Shavuot and so it links the chatas
חטאת chatas to the shalmei tzibur שלמי ציבור. shalmei tzibur. Ma chatas
b'tzafon af shalmei tzibur b'tzafon מה חטאת בצפון אף שלמי ציבור בצפון.
Ma chatas b'tzafon af shalmei tzibur b'tzafon. So since chatas חטאת chatas
is north, shalmei tzibur שלמי ציבור shalmei tzibur is north. Everybody should
be jumping up because, because of the next line of the Gemara
גמרא. Gemara. I hope you have this in your kishkes קישקעס kishkes
at this stage. The Gemara גמרא Gemara says, amar lei Rava אמר
ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, v'chi chatas meihan lamda? וכי חטאת מהיכן
למדה? V'chi chatas meihan lamda? Me'olah מעולה! Me'olah! One minute, we got
chatas חטאת chatas from olah עולה. olah. Davar halamad b'hekesh chozer umelamed
b'hekesh דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? Davar halamad b'hekesh chozer umelamed
b'hekesh? Ha הא! Ha! You gotta know, you're not allowed to do
that. You're not allowed to link and then do another link. Ella
אלא, Ella, it can't be that. Mide'tani Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana
מדיתני רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא, Mide'tani Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana,
now you know why we learned those two daf דף daf before.
Ella אלא, Ella, so you would know that you can't get away
with something like this. Ella mide'tani Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana אלא
מדיתני רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא, Ella mide'tani Rav Mari brei d'Rav
Kahana, al oloteichem v'al zivchei shalmeichem על עולותיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם, Al
oloteichem v'al zivchei shalmeichem, that, you know, this is what you bring
on your olot עולות olot and on your zivchei shalmeichem זבחי שלמיכם,
zivchei shalmeichem, which is, you know, which is interesting, the word zivchei
shalmeichem זבחי שלמיכם zivchei shalmeichem represents, you know, it's the same terminology
that the Rabbis use for these shalmei tzibur שלמי ציבור, shalmei tzibur,
zivchei shalmei tzibur זבחי שלמי ציבור, zivchei shalmei tzibur, you know, it
says—what's the phrase? It says zivchei shalmei tzibur זבחי שלמי ציבור. zivchei
shalmei tzibur. And Rashi רש"י Rashi says we know that this verse
is talking about the... about shelamim שלמים shelamim of the... of the
what do you call it? Because this is about when you use
the chatzotzrot חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, right? And you
blow—right, exactly. And there, I mean it's a little circular, but Chazal
חז"ל Chazal understand that that is only done for korbanot tzibur קרבנות
ציבור korbanot tzibur not korbanot yachid קרבנות יחיד. korbanot yachid. And if
it mentions shelamim שלמים, shelamim, so it must be talking about these
zivchei shalmei tzibur זבחי שלמי ציבור zivchei shalmei tzibur that you bring
on Shavuot שבועות. Shavuot. One minute, fine. Okay. I know, I'm saying
that's why I say Chazal חז"ל Chazal understand, there's nothing explicit in
the pasuk פסוק pasuk that means it's tzibur ציבור, tzibur, Chazal חז"ל
Chazal understand that's talking about tzibur ציבור. tzibur. V'al zivchei shalmeichem ועל
זבחי שלמיכם. V'al zivchei shalmeichem. Ma olah kodshei kodashim af zivchei shalmei
tzibur kodshei kodashim מה עולה קדשי קדשים אף זבחי שלמי ציבור קדשי
קדשים. Ma olah kodshei kodashim af zivchei shalmei tzibur kodshei kodashim. So
there it's linked to an olah עולה. olah. They're both kodshei kodashim
קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. And the basic implication of kodshei kodashim קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim is this issue about the north and that part—more
specifically, it can't be eaten outside of the... of the Temple grounds,
it can only be eaten by male kohanim כהנים. kohanim. So kodshei
kodashim קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Af zivchei shalmei tzibur kodshei kodashim אף
זבחי שלמי ציבור קדשי קדשים. Af zivchei shalmei tzibur kodshei kodashim. Ma
olah b'tzafon af zivchei shalmei tzibur b'tzafon מה עולה בצפון אף זבחי
שלמי ציבור בצפון. Ma olah b'tzafon af zivchei shalmei tzibur b'tzafon. So
they're also both in the north. Af zivchei shalmei tzibur b'tzafon אף
זבחי שלמי ציבור בצפון. Af zivchei shalmei tzibur b'tzafon. Ella אלא, Ella,
so fine. So that's how you learn... that's how you learn it
because of that pasuk פסוק. pasuk. Ella hekesh kamma l'mai ata אלא
היקש קמא למאי אתא? Ella hekesh kamma l'mai ata? So why... what's
the first reason it's linked to a chatas חטאת, chatas, right? The
first pasuk פסוק pasuk we quoted, which is actually the pasuk פסוק
pasuk by Shavuot שבועות Shavuot itself. Why link it to a chatas
חטאת? chatas? And now if you want to explain why it's linked
to a chatas חטאת, chatas, it has to be something we know
from a chatas חטאת chatas itself, it can't be something that we
know because of a chatas חטאת chatas that we learned from somewhere
else. So what is the value of linking it to a chatas
חטאת? chatas? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ella hekesh kamma l'mai
ata? k'chatas אלא היקש קמא למאי אתא? כחטאת, Ella hekesh kamma l'mai
ata? k'chatas, to tell you like a chatas חטאת. chatas. Ma chatas
einah ne'echelet ella l'zichrei kehuna מה חטאת אינה נאכלת אלא לזכרי כהונה,
Ma chatas einah ne'echelet ella l'zichrei kehuna, to tell you this second
part of the idea of it being kodshei kodashim קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, it's only eaten by male kohanim כהנים. kohanim. Af zivchei shalmei
tzibur
l'zichrei kehuna אף זבחי שלמי ציבור לזכרי כהונה Af zivchei shalmei tzibur
l'zichrei kehuna is only by zichrei kehuna זכרי כהונה zichrei kehuna and
you can't do that by linking it to an olah עולה olah
because, why can't you learn out the restriction? An olah עולה olah
isn't eaten. Ah, so it all works out beautifully. Amar lei Abaye
אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. So Abaye אביי Abaye said, i
hachi אי הכי, i hachi, if so, gabei ayil nazir d'chtiv גבי
איל נזיר דכתיב gabei ayil nazir d'chtiv by the ram brought by
the nazir נזיר, nazir, which is a type of a shelamim שלמים
shelamim but it's a private shelamim שלמים, shelamim, and it says the
following by nazir נזיר: nazir: v'hikriv et korbano l'Hashem keves ben shnato
tamim echad l'olah v'chavsa achas bat shnata temima l'chatas v'ayil echad tamim
l'shlamim והקריב את קרבנו לה' כבש בן שנתו תמים אחד לעולה וכבשה
אחת בת שנתה תמימה לחטאת ואיל אחד תמים לשלמים. v'hikriv et korbano
l'Hashem keves ben shnato tamim echad l'olah v'chavsa achas bat shnata temima
l'chatas v'ayil echad tamim l'shlamim. So you have one male sheep for
an olah עולה, olah, a female sheep for a chatas חטאת, chatas,
and one ram for a shelamim שלמים. shelamim. So they're in that
pasuk פסוק pasuk they're linked to the chatas חטאת. chatas. Hacha nami
neima d'hikshah hakatuv l'chatas הכא נמי נימא דהקישה הכתוב לחטאת? Hacha nami
neima d'hikshah hakatuv l'chatas? Ma chatas einah ne'echelet ella l'zichrei kehuna מה
חטאת אינה נאכלת אלא לזכרי כהונה, Ma chatas einah ne'echelet ella l'zichrei
kehuna, af ayil nazir nami einu ne'echal ella l'zichrei kehuna אף איל
נזיר נמי אינו נאכל אלא לזכרי כהונה? af ayil nazir nami einu
ne'echal ella l'zichrei kehuna? וכבשה אחת בת שנתה תמימה לחטאת ואיל אחד
תמים לשלמים, v'chivsah achas bas shnatah temimah l'chatas v'ayil echad tamim l'shlamim,
so you have one male sheep for a חטאת, chatas, a female
sheep for a חטאת, chatas, and one ram for a שלמים. shlamim.
So they're in that פסוק, passuk, they're linked to the חטאת. chatas.
So הכא נמי נימא דהיקשו הכתוב לחטאת מה חטאת אינו נאכל אלא
לזכרי כהונה אף נזיר נמי אינו נאכל אלא לזכרי כהונה? hacha nami
neima dehiksho hakasuv l'chatas mah chatas eino ne'echal ela l'zichrei kehuna af
nazir nami eino ne'echal ela l'zichrei kehuna? Should we say the same
thing, that it's limited to male כהנים, kohanim, whereas this is a
private שלמים, shlamim, why should it be considered קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim
and limited to male כהנים? kohanim? What are you going to do
about the fact that it's linked? Such a pleasure when all of
this is in Mishneic Hebrew, it reads so fast. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says הכי השתא? hachi hasha?
How could you make that comparison? התם כיון דכתיב, hasam keivan dechsiv,
since it's written ולקח הכהן את הזרוע בשלה מן האיל, velakach hakohen
es hazroa beshela min ha-ayil, the כהן kohen his portion is the
cooked arm from the ram. Okay, מכלל, michlal, and so the תורה
Torah says that's what he gets. So the implication is from that
we can infer דכולי בעלים אכלי ליה, dechulei be'alim achlei lei, the
remainder of it is eaten by the owners. So therefore the implication
is this is the כהן's kohen portion, it's a שלמים, shlamim, the
rest is the owner's portion. So you can't say it's only eaten
by the male כהנים. kohanim.
That could be true by the שלמים shlamim brought on שבועות, Shavuos,
but it can't be true here. So therefore there's no basis to
say that this is eaten only by male כהנים kohanim and that
can't be why it's linked to a חטאת. chatas. So the גמרא
Gemara says okay, you know what, that's true about the rest that's
eaten by the owners, that is implied. But זרוע בשלה מי לא
ליתאכלי אלא לזכרי כהונה? zeroa beshela mi lo lishachlei ela l'zichrei kehuna?
But maybe the part that the כהנים kohanim get, maybe that is
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and only eaten by male כהנים? kohanim? Now
we never have anything like that in any קרבן. korban. Either the
whole thing is eaten by the male כהנים, kohanim, or that's קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, or it's קדשים קלים kodshim kalim and most of
it is eaten by the owners and a little bit is eaten
by the כהנים kohanim but it's not limited to male כהנים—we're kohanim
going to see it's their wives, their families, their slaves, and so
on. We'll see about that in a minute. Okay, the household of
the כהנים. kohanim. So you would never have this, such a phenomenon
never exists. But the גמרא Gemara is saying, but if it's linked
to a חטאת, chatas, why not at least say the portion the
כהנים kohanim get is like a חטאת chatas and only eaten by
male כהנים? kohanim? So the גמרא's Gemara answer is קשיא. kashia. ולא
ליתאכלי אלא לזכרי כהונה? ve-lo lishachlei ela l'zichrei kehuna? קשיא, kashia, fine,
that's difficult. But I don't think the גמרא Gemara is so worked
up about it because as I said we don't really have that
phenomenon. Either it's all eaten by male כהנים, kohanim, or if it's
split between owners and the כהנים, kohanim, then the owners eat their
stuff and the כהנים kohanim eat their stuff within their whole family,
not limited to male כהנים. kohanim. So because it's implied that the
owners get the meat, we know that it is not קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim and not limited to male כהנים. kohanim. Okay, the גמרא
Gemara says, but still, why is the שלמים shlamim of the איל
נזיר eil nazir linked to a חטאת? chatas? What do we learn
from that link? So the גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is eima,
קדשי, kodshei,
oh I'm sorry, before we get to that answer, one more reason
why we know that it's not linked, that it's not limited to
male כהנים, kohanim,
because the איל נזיר, eil nazir, קדש איקרי קדשי קדשים לא איקרי.
kodesh ikrei kodshei kodashim lo ikrei. It's never called קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim. So that tells us that it's not one of these things
that's limited to male כהנים. kohanim. Now רש"י Rashi is a little
bothered because זבחי שלמי ציבור zivchei shalmei tzibur also doesn't say קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, it says קדש. kodesh. But at least there it
says קדש לה'. kodesh l'Hashem. So anyway, רש"י Rashi tries to work
out the פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, fine. We know that the link to
a חטאת chatas here is not to tell us only male כהנים.
kohanim. It's קדש, kodesh, it's not קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, it's eaten
by the owners. Fine. So why is the איל נזיר, eil nazir,
the שלמים shlamim of the איל נזיר, eil nazir, linked to a
חטאת? chatas? ולמה הלכתא איתקיש? velama hilchasa itkeish? So for what purpose
is it linked to a חטאת? chatas? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, or
some have רבינא, Ravina, שאם גילח על אחד משלשתן יצא. she-im gilach
al achad me-shloshtan yatza. The link is actually to tell you the
opposite direction, that the שלמים, shlamim, the איל נזיר, eil nazir, the
שלמים shlamim is framed in the פסוקים psukim as the central קרבן
korban for ending the נזירות nezirus because it says he shaves his
head, he puts it under the pot which is cooking the arm
of the איל נזיר, eil nazir, that's why זרוע בשלה, zeroa beshela,
you cook it in a pot and you put his hair under
the pot. So there's a clear intertwining of the איל נזיר, eil
nazir, the שלמים, shlamim, with his shaving his hair and with his
ending his נזירות. nezirus. There's other reasons, other bases of other things
in the פסוקים psukim also that seem to link them, that רש"י
Rashi talks about. So therefore the פסוק pasuk links it to a
חטאת, chatas, not that you should say a law of a חטאת
chatas applies to this, but to go in the reverse direction. That
the same way this thing basically ends the נזירות, nezirus, if you
shaved in the context of bringing this, even if you did not
yet bring the איל נזיר—this eil nazir is pretty shocking—and you just
brought the חטאת chatas mentioned earlier, one of the חטאות chataos mentioned
earlier, and you did it, you're also end your נזירות. nezirus. Okay,
so that is a big חדוש, chiddush, that this is not, it's
not that the whole sort of ending of the נזירות nezirus is
all dependent on this one קרבן. korban.
Okay, next משנה. Mishnah. So that is the end of our קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Now we go to our קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim,
and before we get to this sort of most generic of those
categories which is the שלמים, shlamim, we start with one or two
things which are sort of like שלמים, shlamim, but they are a
little bit more distinct. Okay, התודה, Ha-Todah, the תודה, Todah, which is
something that is brought when for purpose of thanksgiving. חז"ל Chazal enumerate
four circumstances which you bring it. It's a type of a שלמים
shlamim but you also bring forty loaves of bread, thirty of which
are מצה, matzah, ten of which are חמץ. chametz. You give a
כהן kohen one out of each group of ten, so a כהן
kohen gets, there are four different, there are four different types of
bread. Three different types of מצה, matzah, one type of חמץ. chametz.
So a כהן kohen gets one out of each ten. Okay, so
that's the תודה. Todah. איל נזיר Eil Nazir we just mentioned. That's
a type of a שלמים shlamim but you have this special ritual
with the hair, it's brought for a נזיר, nazir, the כהן kohen
gets not only the normal things that a כהן kohen would get
from a שלמים, shlamim, he also gets the זרוע בשלה. zeroa beshela.
So in both of these the כהן Kohen gets something extra. By
the תודה Toda he gets the bread, one loaf of each bread,
and by the איל נזיר Eil Nazir he gets the arm. Normal
שלמים shelamim is you take the, you know, the חזה chazeh and
the שוק, shok, the breast and the thigh, right, and you wave
it and that you give to the כהן. Kohen. So this is
true by these but these also have something a little extra given
to the כהן. Kohen. Put in a little extra for you. Okay
anyway so קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim ואיל נזיר veEil Nazir קדשים קלים.
Kodshim Kalim. שחיטתן בכל מקום בעזרה. Shechitatan bechol makom ba'azarah. Now finally
we're getting a difference because this is קדשים קלים. Kodshim Kalim. You
don't have to, you're not limited to the north. You שחט shecht
them anywhere. ודמן טעון שתי מתנות שהן ארבע, Vedaman taun shtei matan
shehen arba, still the same as two that is four, which is
true by everything that's on a חטאת. chatas. ונאכלים בכל העיר. Vene'echalim
bechol ha'ir. Here's another difference. Not limited to the temple courtyard, to
the עזרה, azarah, can be eaten in the entire city of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, לכל אדם, lechol adam, can be eaten by anybody, it's
not limited to being eaten by כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, men, women, yes
כהן, Kohen, not כהן, Kohen, okay, בכל מאכל bechol ma'achal in any
form, it doesn't have to be like roasted like a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. ליום ולילה, Leyom valaylah, now here's another way it's different
than a שלמים. shelamim. A שלמים shelamim is eaten for two days
and the intervening night. A תודה Toda and the איל נזיר Eil
Nazir is eaten only for the day and the following night, okay,
it says that explicitly by the תודה, Toda, alright, and therefore we're
going to, the איל נזיר Eil Nazir is linked to the תודה,
Toda, I mean whatever חז"ל Chazal read within the פרשה Parsha of
a תודה Toda that it indicates the איל נזיר Eil Nazir as
well, so because of these are distinctive types of שלמים, shelamim, it's
only the day and the following night. Now the real הלכה Halacha
is the entire following night, but חז"ל Chazal said עד חצות, ad
chatzos, until midnight so it would not lead you to falling asleep.
המורם מהם כיוצא בהם. Hamuram mehem kiyotei bahem. Now the stuff that
is lifted up from them, the תרומה, terumah, right, which is sometimes
שוק התרומה וחזה התנופה, shok haterumah vechazeh hatenufah, right, the stuff that
is given to the כהן Kohen has the same הלכה, Halacha, the
same הלכה Halacha in the sense that it is eaten in all
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, it's not limited to the grounds of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But there is a difference and here's the
difference, the difference is that oh and it's eaten you know for
that day and for the day and the following night, so it
follows the same הלכה, Halacha, okay, but here's the difference.
It says אלא שהמורם נאכל לכהנים לנשיהם ולבניהם ולעבדיהם. ela shehamuram ne'echal
lakohanim lenasheihem velivneihem vela'avdeihem. It is not limited to male כהנים. Kohanim.
It is like it goes to the whole family of כהנים, Kohanim,
their wives, their kids, and their slaves. Now what other thing are
do כהנים Kohanim eat that is like this? That is meaning קדש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim the חטאת chatas is eaten in the temple courtyard
by male כהנים. Kohanim. What thing is limited is restricted to the
eating of the כהנים Kohanim but can be eaten by תרומה. Terumah.
תרומה. Terumah. So this is just like תרומה Terumah and therefore it's
appropriate that it says המורם מהם hamuram mehem like the that which
is lifted up, שוק התרומה. shok haterumah. Okay so the
תורה Torah says like לכל בניך אתך ולבניך ולבנתיך. lechol banecha itcha
ulevanecha velivnotecha. The פסוק pasuk actually says to you and your daughters
and your sons and your daughters, it explicitly mentions daughters. Okay so
it is limited to כהנים Kohanim and the כהן Kohen family, it
can't be eaten by ישראל. Yisrael. It's still also different than תרומה
Terumah because תרומה Terumah is called קדשי הגבול. kodshei hagvul. קדשי הגבול
Kodshei hagvul
means that it could be eaten anywhere in the you know boundaries
of of ישראל Israel whereas this although it is like תרומה Terumah
in the sense of its קדושה kedusha and you know it's allowed
it can't be eaten by ישראל Yisrael but it can be eaten
by the whole family of the כהנים, Kohanim, okay, it is still
not קדשי גבול kodshei gvul because it can only be eaten in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can't take it out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. תרומה Terumah
of course is not restricted to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the בכל מאכל
bechol ma'achal part which we had already before in the previous משנה
mishna yeah this is coming to teach you not doesn't limit it
to the meaning you might have thought that you might have it's
just another thing to say about it. I don't know why it
has to keep on repeating it, because when it gets to פסח
Pesach it's going to say it's only נאכל צלי. ne'echal tli. Okay
I guess it was just interested exactly. You know just trying to
make a chart, you know, and by פסח Pesach it's going to
be only צלי tli so you need to have blanks in the
other parts of the chart. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, את חזה
התנופה ואת שוק התרומה תאכלו במקום. eis chazeh hatenufah ve'eis shok haterumah
tochlu bemakom. So now we're going to look at how do you
know this idea that it is it's eaten only in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
out meaning both limited to ירושלים Yerushalayim but outside of the temple
courtyard. Because the פסוק pasuk says like this: את חזה התנופה eis
chazeh hatenufah and that you mean like not just the whole temple,
like the even עזרת נשים? Ezras Nashim? This is, to say it
again, this is, right, the עזרה. Azarah. When I say the temple
courtyard, it is does not include the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim has the status of מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, of
הר הבית. Har Habayis. Okay, so it is only from where the
actual קרבנות, korbanot, you know, I mean it's a little bit more
back because it's not right up against the מזבח, mizbeach, but anyway,
but it's only like where the קרבנות korbanot can be slaughtered, even
קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim can only be slaughtered in the עזרה, Azarah,
they can't be slaughtered out of the עזרה, Azarah, right, this is
where all the everything is done, okay, this is the only place
that the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim can be eaten. The קדש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim can only be eaten in the place directly where the
עבודה avodah is done. Cannot be eaten in the עזרת נשים. Ezras
Nashim. So there had to have been some sort of like kitchen
facilities so to speak. I mean, you know. Yeah. So you can
so you can roast it, you can, you know, spice it, you
can they did. There was one of those chambers that they had
there was exactly a place where they cook. But they had to
stand up, right? Because you're not allowed to sit in the the
עזרה. Azarah. So they had to eat it standing up presumably. I'm
just like thinking about it. I'm just thinking about like the meal
that they'd have. Like you know they have some of the מנחה,
mincha, you know. They'd make it into whatever it is. That's a
good point, I hadn't thought about that, but that's a good point.
Yeah, because you're right, אין ישיבה בעזרה. ein yeshiva ba-azarah. Okay, so
there's three מחנות, machanos, right? I mean, you know, here is, this
is מחנה שכינה, machane shechina, okay, and this is actually the עזרה,
azarah, okay, and this is the עזרה, azarah, right? It's basically, here's
your little מזבח, mizbeach, whatever, okay, okay. Then this is מחנה לויה,
machane leviyah, this is הר הבית, Har HaBayis,
okay. The wall, actually, the Western Wall, I mean, I guess it's
called western like this, right, the Western Wall here is actually the
wall around הר הבית, Har HaBayis, okay. And then here's all of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So actually, the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, you know, this,
is הר הבית, Har HaBayis, it is not the actual עזרה. azarah.
Okay, so anyway, okay, so this is, so how do you know
that this is eaten out of the עזרה azarah and in all
of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: את חזה התנופה ואת שוק
התרומה תאכלו במקום טהור. Es chaze hatenufa ve'es shok hateruma tochlu bemakom
tahor. אמר רבי נחמיה: Amar Rabi Nechemya: וכי ראשונים בטומאה אכלום? vechi
rishonim betumah achlum? What do you mean? Oh this you eat in
a טהור tahor place. What? So the קדשי קדשים kadishei kodashim you
ate in טומאה? tumah? I mean, so the point is that טהור
tahor here is not saying that it's more טהור tahor than the
rest, it's saying it's only טהור tahor and it's not קדוש, kadosh,
because the other stuff it says תאכלו במקום קדוש, tochlu bemakom kadosh,
and here it says תאכלו במקום טהור. tochlu bemakom tahor. Okay, so,
so this is actually, this is בשמיני, be-Shemini, this is Moshe giving
the command to, you know, Aaron and his kids, okay, by the
קרבנות korbanos that they would bring, you know, that they brought on
שמיני. Shemini. So it says וכי—so vechi but this is by specifically
by the, you know, by the שלמים. shlamim. So it says—That's in
that pasuk. What? That's that פסוק pasuk in the one you quoted.
What? What do you mean?
What mentions what? את חזה התנופה ואת שוק התרומה, Es chaze hatenufa
ve'es shok hateruma, that mentions שלמים shlamim in that פסוק. pasuk. Right,
right. Here, I'll read it.
That was right before he asked what happened to the חטאת. chatas.
You weren't listening to me. Okay.
ואכלתם אותה—so Va'achaltem osah it says like this, listen to the פסוק
pasuk because actually it's worth reading because it reinforces this whole distinction
of קדשי קדשים kadishei kodashim and קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. וידבר משה
אל אהרן, Vayedaber Moshe el Aharon, this is י, Yud, יב, Yud-Beis,
ואל אלעזר ואל איתמר בניו הנותרים קחו את המנחה הנותרת מאשי ה'
ואכלוה מצות אצל המזבח כי
קדש קדשים היא. ve'el Elazar ve'el Isamar banav hanosarim kechu es hamincha
hanoseres me'ishei Hashem ve'achluha matzos eitzel hamizbeach ki kodesh kodashim hi. So
the מנחה mincha is קדשי קדשים. kadishei kodashim. ואכלתם אותה במקום קדוש,
Va'achaltem osah bemakom kadosh, eat it in a holy place. כי חקך
וחק בניך היא מאשי ה' כי כן צויתי. Ki chokcha vechok banecha
hi me'ishei Hashem ki chein tzuveisi. ואת חזה התנופה ואת שוק התרומה
תאכלו במקום טהור אתה ובניך ובנותיך אתך כי חקך וחק בניך נתנו
מזבחי שלמי בני ישראל. Ve'es chaze hatenufa ve'es shok hateruma tochlu bemakom
tahor ata uvenei'cha uvenoseicha itacha ki chokcha vechok banecha nisnu mizivchei shalmei
benei Yisrael. Okay,
so notice what it says, במקום—maybe bemakom that's what you meant by—טהור,
tahor, אתה ובניך ובנותיך אתך. ata uvenei'cha uvenoseicha itacha.
So this doesn't say קדשי קדשים היא, kadishei kodashim hi, right, it
says חקך, chokcha, but it doesn't say קדשי קדשים היא, kadishei kodashim
hi, it says you and your daughters, okay, and it says תאכלו
במקום טהור tochlu bemakom tahor as contrasted to מקום קדוש. makom kadosh.
Right, and it's a שלמים. shlamim. Right, and it's a שלמים, shlamim,
right. So this is exactly, you know, the distinction, שוק התרומה וחזה
התנופה, shok hateruma vechaze hatenufa, על חלבי האשים יביאו להניף תנופה ויהיה
לך ולבניך אתך לחק עולם כאשר צוה ה', al chelvei ha'ishim yaviu
lehanif tenufa vehaya lecha ulevanecha itacha lechok olam ka'asher tziva Hashem, fine.
Okay, so this is exactly drawing those lines between קדשי קדשים, kadishei
kodashim, קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, who gets to eat them and where
you get to eat them, מקום קדוש makom kadosh or מקום טהור.
makom tahor. את חזה התנופה ואת שוק התרומה תאכלו במקום טהור. Es
chaze hatenufa ve'es shok hateruma tochlu bemakom tahor. אמר רבי נחמיה: Amar
Rabi Nechemya: וכי ראשונים בטומאה אכלום? vechi rishonim betumah achlum? What? So
the holier stuff was eaten בטומאה? betumah? Obviously not. אלא טהור מכלל
שהוא טמא. Ella tahor miklal shehu tamei. You gotta love what the
גמרא Gemara does there. טהור Tahor means it's a little bit טהור.
tahor. Me thinks she doth protest too much. טהור, Tahor, it's a
little, it's also a little טמא, tamei, it's not totally טהור. tahor.
You know, I don't know if I would have said that. I
would have said טהור tahor means it's not as קדוש, kadosh, because
טהור tahor is contrasted to קדוש. kadosh. It's only טהור, tahor, it's
not also קדוש. kadosh. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says it allows for
a certain degree of טומאה. tumah. טהור מטומאת מצורע וטמא מטומאת זב.
Tahor mitumas metzora vetamei mitumas zav. So ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can't have
מצורעים metzoraim in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they have to be sent outside of
three מחנות, machanos, so, but it's טמא tamei in that you can
allow other people that are טמא tamei to be in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
A זב zav can be in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, a dead body can
be in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, a טמא מת tamei meis can be in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and by the way, you know, partly I think maybe
that's why the גמרא Gemara is saying this is that if it
would have just said טהור tahor but not קדוש, kadosh, so fine,
that would have said it doesn't have to be on the temple
grounds, but then you would have said wait, why is ירושלים Yerushalayim
being called a מקום טהור? makom tahor? According to הלכה, halacha, right,
ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't have to be totally cleansed of all טומאה, tumah,
actually almost all טומאה tumah is allowed in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The only
טמא tamei thing that's not allowed in ירושלים Yerushalayim is a מצורע.
metzora. So it almost was forced to say, it's almost like an
intrinsic problem. How could we be calling מקום טהור makom tahor a
place that according to חז"ל Chazal pretty much all טומאות tumos are
allowed to be there? So the answer is, okay, most טומאות, tumos,
but not all טומאות, tumos, so it still has an element of
טהור. tahor. טהור מכלל שהוא טמא. Tahor miklal shehu tamei. Okay, טהור
מטומאת
מצורע וטמא מטומאת זב. tahor mitumas metzora vetamei mitumas zav. And as
I'm saying also, it's also not קדוש kadosh in the same way.
Yeah, but how do you know it's not like the הר הבית?
Har HaBayis? So the גמרא Gemara is going to ask that. ואיזה
זה מחנה ישראל? Ve'eizeh zeh machane Yisrael? That's the camp of ישראל
Yisrael which corresponded to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואימא טהור מטומאת זב וטמא מטומאת
מת? Ve'eima tahor mitumas zav vetamei mitumas meis? ואיזה זה מחנה לויה?
V'eizeh zeh Machaneh Leviyah? Oh, one minute, if it's maybe it means
it has to be more טהור, tahor, not the minimalist טהור. tahor.
Maybe it has to be טהור tahor like מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah.
And that, you're allowed to have a dead body or a person
טמא tamei to a dead body there, but you're not allowed to
have a זב, zav, somebody with a flow in מחנה לויה. Machaneh
Leviyah. So maybe that's what it means, at least that's more significantly
טהור. tahor. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says ואכלתם אתה במקום קדוש. v'achaltem otah b'makom kadosh. This is by
the חטאת. chatas. אתה במקום קדוש ולא אחרת במקום קדוש. otah b'makom
kadosh v'lo acheret b'makom kadosh, Now we're getting to the fact that
it's not, its contrast to the מקום קדוש, makom kadosh, not so
much intrinsic in the word טהור, tahor, but the contrast to קדוש.
kadosh. חטאת Chatas is in a קדוש, kadosh, which means that the
other stuff doesn't have to be a holy place. So even before
it said טהור tahor by the חזה התנופה, chazeh hatenufah, even before
it said that I knew that it was emphasizing חטאת chatas is
קדוש. kadosh. This doesn't have to be in the temple grounds. Okay?
אפקי לה למחנה לויה, Afkei leh l'Machaneh Leviyah, so just by saying
that a חטאת chatas is קדוש kadosh and using the limiting word
אתה otah is telling, would tell me that the שלמים shlamim did
not have to be in מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, could be in
מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, could be which would correspond to הר הבית.
Har Habayit. That I knew already. הדר כתב במקום טהור Hadar ktav
b'makom tahor and then the פסוק pasuk says, oh eat this in
מקום טהור, makom tahor, so that's coming to even tell you you
even have more latitude. Okay? And therefore אפקי
לה למחנה ישראל. afkei leh l'Machaneh Yisrael. Then it brought it out
into מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. I already knew it wasn't going to
be in on the in the עזרה azarah itself, I already knew
הר הבית, Har Habayit, and then it said it doesn't really have
to be קדוש kadosh at all, just טהור. tahor. Or טהור tahor
means that it has an element of טומאה tumah and that allows
me to say all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Okay. אמר, Amar, so that's אביי's Abaye read. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, which is a nice read. רבא Rava says אתה במקום קדוש
otah b'makom kadosh ולא אחרת במקום קדוש, v'lo acheret b'makom kadosh. אפקי
לגמרי. afkei legamrei. He starts the same way. אתה Otah means the
חטאת chatas is in a holy place, but not the שלמים, shlamim,
so that would have led me to say the שלמים shlamim is
in can be eaten anywhere, even out of מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael,
could be in anywhere in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. הדר כתב רחמנא
תאכלו במקום טהור. Hadar ktav Rachamana tochelu b'makom tahor. Now מקום טהור
makom tahor is coming to limit it, pull it back in. עייליה
למחנה ישראל, Ailah l'Machaneh Yisrael, but we pull it back in to
one degree, we pull it back in just to מחנה ישראל, Machaneh
Yisrael, to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואימא
עייליה למחנה לויה? v'eima ailah l'Machaneh Leviyah? If it's pulling it back
in, maybe it pulls it back in even closer all the way
to מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לחדא
מעלינן לתרתי לא מעלינן. l'chada mailinan l'tartei lo mailinan. No no, we're
only going to bring it in one stage, not two stages. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי אפוקי נמי לחדא מפקינן לתרתי לא
מפקינן? ei hachi afukei nami l'chada mafkinan l'tartei lo mafkinan? So when
you learned out אתה במקום קדוש otah b'makom kadosh and you said
oh, so this something else can be in out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
why do you jump all the way out? Why don't you just
also say one degree out? If you're basically a minimalist and going
to say any דרשה drasha is going to tell me remove it
one degree, move it one degree, so then your initial דרשה drasha
should have only moved it one degree, which is what אביי Abaye
did. Right? Rather than saying that because it says a חטאת chatas
is במקום קדוש b'makom kadosh I would have thought a שלמים shlamim
is completely out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so that a doesn't make sense.
ועוד, V'od, there wouldn't could never have been a הוה אמינא hava
amina that you could eat a קרבן korban outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
outside of מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. Why? Because it says לא תוכל
לאכל בשעריך, lo tuchal l'echol b'sharecha, right, מעשר דגנך ותירושך ויצהרך ונדריך
ונדבותיך אשר תדר, ma'asar deganecha v'tiroshecha v'yitzharecha u'nedarecha u'nedavotecha asher tidor,
you can't eat in your gates, meaning in your stam cities you
can't eat קדשים. kodshim. Okay, that it can only be eaten in
the one central place. אלא מחוורתא כדאביי, Ela michavrta k'Abaye, we like
אביי's Abaye דרשה drasha better. Okay,
so אתה במקום קדוש otah b'makom kadosh implies שלמים shlamim outside of
the עזרה azarah and then טהור tahor pulls it even further out
and says anywhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now we get to the broadest
category of קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, שלמים. shlamim. שלמים קדשים קלים שחיטתם
בכל מקום בעזרה, Shlamim kodshim kalim shechitatam bechol makom ba'azarah, ודמן טעון
שתי מתנות שהן ארבע, v'daman ta'un shtei matanot shehen arba,
so it's anywhere in the עזרה, azarah, two that are four, ונאכלין
בכל העיר v'ne'echalin bechol ha'ir in anywhere, לכל אדם בכל מאכל, l'chol
adam bechol ma'achal, anybody can eat it, any type of way of
preparing it, לשני ימים ולילה אחד. l'shnei yamim v'laila echad. Here it's
finally here's the one difference from the thing above is that it
is eaten two days and the intervening night, so no חצות. chatzot.
You don't need to tell me don't fall asleep in the middle
of the day. Okay, so therefore המורם מהם כיוצא בהם, hamuram mehem
kayotze bahem, the stuff that's given from it to the כהנים, kohanim,
the חזה chazeh and the שוק, shok, have the same הלכות. halachot.
אלא שהמורם נאכל לכהנים ולנשיהם ולבניהם ולעבדיהם, Ela shehamuram ne'echal l'kohanim u'lensheihem
u'livneihem u'l'avdeihem, it's just not eaten, it's eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim but
not eaten by all people, it's limited to the families of the
כהנים. kohanim. Anyway the חצות, chatzot, הרחקת אדם מן העבירה, harchakat adam
min ha'aveira, really the whole night. Right. Right. I said that before.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Now we're going to use this as an
opportunity, we could have said this in the previous משנה, mishnah, but
we're dividing it up to discuss the idea of how do you
know that this could be slaughtered anywhere in the עזרה? azarah? Okay?
And the simple answer is that it doesn't say north. But when
it does talk about slaughtering it, it specifically speaks about slaughtering it
פתח אהל מועד, petach Ohel Moed, which is a very broad definition.
Okay? Anywhere in front of the door, which is not specifically the
north. Although if it's limited to פתח אהל מועד, petach Ohel Moed,
you're going to wonder what about here? What about here? What about
here? The sides. We're going to get to that. Okay? But it
doesn't say north and it does say
פתח אהל מועד. petach Ohel Moed.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. ושחטו פתח אהל מועד. V'shachatu petach Ohel Moed.
ושחטו אתו. V'shachato oto. Maybe it's
ושחטו. v'shachatu. ושחטתו. V'shachattato. Maybe it's ושחטתו? V'shachattato? Yes, ושחטתו. V'shachattato.
ושחטתו פתח אהל מועד. V'shachattato Petach Ohel Moed. Slaughter it by the
opening of
אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. ושחטו אותו לפני, V'shachato oto lifnei, a number
of those actually. Right. These are all, it says all these by
שלמים Shlamim because it talks about different שלמים, Shlamim, and every time
it talks about a שלמים Shlamim in the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra,
it says "the opening of אהל מועד". Ohel Moed It never says
north and it always says the opening of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
ושחטו אותו לפני אהל מועד. V'shachato oto lifnei Ohel Moed. So להכשיר,
l'hachshir, so you have three פסוקים. psukim. את כל הרוחות בקדשים קלים,
et kol haruchot b'kodashim kalim, any direction. Okay. קל וחומר לצפון. Kal
vachomer l'tzafon. Now, three gives you three directions, but there are four
directions. So we don't need a פסוק pasuk for the north because
we can learn it as a קל וחומר kal vachomer from קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay.
ומה קדשי קדשים שלא הוכשרו בכל הרוחות, U'mah kodshei kodashim shelo huchsharu
b'chol haruchot, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim cannot be in all directions. They
can only be in the north.
הוכשרו בצפון, huchsharu b'tzafon, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are limited to the
north. קדשים קלים שהוכשרו בכל הרוחות, kodashim kalim shehuchsharu b'chol haruchot, קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim that you have given latitude wherever you want, אינו
דין שהוכשרו בצפון, eino din shehuchsharu b'tzafon, certainly it's in the north.
So you don't need a פסוק pasuk for the north, the פסוקים
psukim tell you for the other direction. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, Rabbi Eliezer says,
לא נאמר הכתוב אלא להכשיר צפון. lo ne'emar hakatuv ela l'hachshir tzafon.
No, no, no, you needed one of those three פסוקים psukim is
needed specifically to tell you it's allowed to be in the north.
Why would I have thought it's not allowed to be in the
north? שיחלוף עליו הדין. sheyachlof alav hadin. I could make a קל
וחומר kal vachomer the opposite way. ומה קדשים קלים שהוכשרו בכל הרוחות
לא הוכשרו במקום שחיטת קדשי קדשים. U'mah kodashim kalim shehuchsharu b'chol haruchot
lo huchsharu bimkom shechitat kodshei kodashim. So קדשים קלים kodashim kalim can
be in any direction. But where they can be, קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim can't be. Where קדשים קלים kodashim kalim are allowed, קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim are not allowed. So then I could say the reverse.
Where קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is allowed, קדשים קלים kodashim kalim are
not allowed.
Okay. קדשי קדשים שלא הוכשרו אלא בצפון, kodshei kodashim shelo huchsharu ela
b'tzafon, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim which are only the north, אינו דין
שלא הוכשרו במקום שחיטת קדשים קלים? eino din shelo huchsharu bimkom shechitat
kodashim kalim? So since קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are weightier, maybe their
space should be reserved for them. Okay. And therefore, not קדשים קלים.
kodashim kalim. Okay. תלמוד לומר אהל מועד. Talmud lomar Ohel Moed. So
you need a פסוק pasuk to tell me yes. So the way
רש"י Rashi puts this, רש"י Rashi actually says, look, says רש"י, Rashi,
there's no special קדושה kedusha of the north. It's all arbitrary. So
it's not like, oh, well, if קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, you know,
so if it's all arbitrary, maybe the תורה Torah wants to give
separate zones for each קרבן, korban, which is a very reasonable point.
So just קדשי... so, you know, so just because קדשים קלים kodoshim
kalim. are less restrictive in general, you have more spaces, doesn't mean
that you can infer that you can encroach on the space that
maybe that space should be designated for קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Which
is a very good reasonable argument. Okay, but in the end we
all agree to the הלכה. halacha. So the גמרא Gemara says
במאי קמיפלגי? b'mai kamiflagi?
What do they debate? תנא קמא סבר תלתא קראי כתיבי. Tanna Kamma
savar tlata krai ktivi. Three פסוקים. psukim. חד לגופיה. Chad l'gufeh. You
need by פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed. One is פתח אהל
מועד Petach Ohel Moed just says it has to be in front
of פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, which means that if you
don't have it functioning as a פתח, petach, it doesn't work. And
we're going to get to that later in the דף. daf. For
example, in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, if the door was locked
or closed before they would open the doors of אהל מועד Ohel
Moed first thing in the morning, open for business. Yeah, by אהל
מועד Ohel Moed I don't mean open the doors to let people
in. People aren't meant, the doors here, that would give access to
the כהנים kohanim to go inside of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So
number one, if the doors are locked. Number two, if the base...
if the temple in the משכן Mishkan was being deconstructed or reconstructed
and then you hadn't yet constructed the opening. Okay, there needs to
be an opening and the door has to be open in order
to do the שחיטה shechitah of קרבנות. korbanot. So the קרבנות korbanot
that were שחט shechted in the morning before the doors of the,
you know, אולם Ulam were open are actually פסול, pasul, okay? So,
so that's number one, דבעי פתח אהל מועד. d'ba'ei Petach Ohel Moed.
וחד להכשיר צדדין. V'chad l'hachshir tzdadin. The other question is, okay, what
maybe it would have to be directly here פתח אהל מועד, Petach
Ohel Moed, like like directly in front, right opposite the door? How
do I know...
right?
So maybe it has to be like right over here, right where
the door is. How do I know that if it's here it's
okay, you know, or here it's okay, or here, or here? Right?
And what we're going to really ask is how do I know
if it's back here because at least these see the door by
an angle. It's not directly opposite the door, but at least they're,
you know, you can make a straight line to connect them to
the door. Okay? So we'll get to how he knows this stuff
in a minute. Okay, but right now we're going to focus on
there. How do you know the side? So another פסוק pasuk says
פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, you know, or לפני אהל מועד
lifnei Ohel Moed to give you more latitude. And since one of
them doesn't even mention פתח, petach, that's also part of the problem.
Right? One just says לפני אהל מועד. lifnei Ohel Moed. So פתח
petach implies the door and an open door. לפני lifnei gives you
more latitude. וחד להכשיר צדדין. V'chad l'hachshir tzdadin. וחד V'chad and the
final one, and the final one says... no,
both of them say לפני אהל מועד. lifnei Ohel Moed. But anyway,
somehow the third one we're going to learn as a limiting פסוק
pasuk and
rather than a more inclusive פסוק, pasuk, to insist that it still
be an element of לפני אהל מועד, lifnei Ohel Moed, so therefore
לפסול צידי צדדין, lifsol tzidei tzadadin, the sides of the sides. What
are the sides of the sides? So again, I would have imagined
it meant behind the door. That actually we're going to say is
not. But רש״י Rashi actually says it's coming to do is coming
to say, let's say the כהן kohein is in a room here,
they would have a room off the side, okay, and maybe this
is where, like as Michael was saying, where they would cook the
שלמים shelamim or where they would cook the חטאת chatat or whatever
it would be. So why don't you say, well I'm in front
of אהל מועד, ohel moed, like geographically I'm in front of אהל
מועד, ohel moed, I'm in a wall, I have walls I can't
see it, okay, so the answer is no, that doesn't count. The
third לפני אהל מועד lifnei ohel moed is telling you that you
have to be directly, you have to be לפני, lifnei, there really
has to be a sense of presence, you know,
so therefore being in a room, which is what we're calling צידי
צדדים, tzidei tzdadim, that doesn't count. But we are going to say
that this stuff behind the door actually does count as לפני, lifnei,
that's gonna be a חידוש, chidush, we'll get to that in a
minute. Okay. That's what you do for the three פסוקים. psukim.
וחד
וחד, vechad vechad, okay, וצפון לא אצטריך קרא, vetzafon lo itztarich kra,
and צפון tzafon doesn't need a פסוק. pasuk. So we really as
opposed to the way it sounded that three פסוקים psukim are three
directions, we're really not saying that. One פסוק pasuk is a door,
the other פסוק pasuk tells you any direction, and the third פסוק
pasuk tells you not צידי צדדים. tzidei tzdadim. So really one פסוק
pasuk was enough to tell you any direction, but you and the
point is you don't need to say, wait, maybe any direction but
north, maybe north is reserved? No, this approach says we don't start
with an assumption that north is reserved. So you don't need a
פסוק pasuk to address the north issue. Okay. וצפון לא אצטריך
קרא. vetzafon lo itztarich kra. רבי אליעזר סבר, Rabbi Eliezer savar, Rabbi
Eliezer holds, חד לגופיה דבעינן פתח אהל מועד, chad leguifei d'ba'inan petach
ohel moed, one for telling you it's got to be a door
and it's got to be open, וחד להכשיר צפון, vechad lehachshir tzafon,
no, I would have thought north is reserved, so I need one
פסוק pasuk to tell me north is not reserved, וחד להכשיר צדדים,
vechad lehachshir tzdadim, and one is to tell me not only north,
anywhere and even not directly in front, even a little off to
the sides,
וצידי צדדים לא אצטריך קרא, vetzidei tzdadim lo itztarich kra, I don't
need a פסוק pasuk to exclude צידי צדדים. tzidei tzdadim. Somebody's in
some room, that to me is obviously not לפני אהל מועד, lifnei
ohel moed, I don't need a פסוק pasuk for it. Okay, so
at the end of the day we all agree it's just a
question how you get there. Did you start by assuming that north
had to be reserved or not and did you need a פסוק
pasuk to exclude the idea that if you're in a room it
doesn't count? A separate room. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: מאי שנא הכא דכתיב פתח אהל מועד ומאי שנא התם דכתיב
לפני אהל מועד, mai shna hacha d'chtiv petach ohel moed u'mai shna
hatam d'chtiv lifnei ohel moed, meaning so what's the emphasis of the
word פתח? petach? Okay, now we're just going to go back to
sort of expand what we said before, that there has to be
a doorway and it has to be open. So the גמרא Gemara
says: קא משמע לן כדרב יהודה אמר שמואל דאמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל שלמים ששחטן קודם שיפתחו דלתות ההיכל פסולין. ka mashma lan k'd'Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel shelamim sheshchatan kodem sheyiptechu
daltot haheichal psulin. If they are slaughtered before the doors of the
היכל, heichal, I meant to say the אולם ulam before, but obviously
the היכל heichal is the אהל מועד ohel moed proper, right? The
אולם ulam is an addition that you didn't have in the משכן,
mishkan, the actual אהל מועד, ohel moed, you know, is the היכל.
heichal. So if they are slaughtered before the doors of the היכל
heichal would be opened, they are invalid. And actually in the משניות
mishnayot where it discusses how they would start the day, one of
the first things it speaks about is a כהן kohein that would
go through a tiny little door to allow him to open up
the doors of the אולם ulam and then the doors of the
היכל heichal so that they can then start the day with doing
the שחיטה. shchita. There's something very nice about the idea, like, you
know, the doors to the king's palace are open. Like before you
do the שחיטה shchita out here, there has to be like access,
you know, like the door, you know, if you I mean obviously
it's anthropomorphic but if you think about like this is where God
resides, right, in whatever, you're not going to be offering sacrifices before
the doors are open. Okay.
Okay fine.
So if it's before they're open, they're פסולים, psulim, שנאמר ושחטו פתח
אהל מועד, shene'emar v'shachato petach ohel moed, בזמן שהוא פתוח, bizman shehu
patuach, it has to be, it has to be open, ולא בזמן
שהוא נעול, v'lo bizman shehu naul, not when it's locked. אי נמי
אמר מר עוקבא בר חמא אמר רב יוסי בר חנינא שלמים ששחטן
קודם שיפתחו דלתות היכל פסולין שנאמר ושחטו פתח אהל מועד בזמן שפתח
אהל מועד פתוח ולא בזמן שהוא נעול, i nami amar Mar Ukva
bar Chama amar Rav Yossi bar Chanina shelamim sheshchatan kodem sheyiptechu daltot
heichal psulin shene'emar v'shachato petach ohel moed bizman shepetach ohel moed patuach
v'lo bizman shehu naul, not when it's locked. בר מרוא מתני לה
אהא דתלתין, Bar Maru'a masni la aha d'taltin, it's like three things
all saying the same thing. הכי אמר רב יעקב בר אחא אמר
רב אשי שלמים ששחטן קודם שיפתחו דלתות היכל
פסולין. hachi amar Rav Yaakov bar Acha amar Rav Ashi shelamim sheshchatan
kodem sheyiptechu daltot heichal psulin. If they're slaughtered before it's open,
it's invalid. ובמשכן קודם שיעמידו לויים את המשכן, u'vamishkan kodem sheya'amidu leviim
et hamishkan, now we're having a little more elaboration, if they were
slaughtered before the לויים leviim erected the משכן, mishkan, before there actually
was the structure. You know, maybe you had the outer what do
you call
it curtain, but you didn't have the actual structure of the אהל
מועד, ohel moed, so you didn't have a פתח, petach, ולאחר שפרקו
לויים את המשכן, u'le'achar shepirku leviim et hamishkan,
or if they removed, undid the structure of the אהל מועד ohel
moed even if you still had the outer curtains, it would be
invalid, פסולים. psulin.
Now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand what is exactly the definition
of open. Okay. פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious, says the גמרא, Gemara, מוגף,
mugaf, if it is the door is closed, כנעול דמי, kenaul dami,
it's like it's locked. That's a fascinating question, right? When do you
need unlocked and when do you need open? So the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, questions about, you know, a lot of things, יחוד,
yichud, other types of questions, right? Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
if the door is closed, it's not פתוח, patuach, a פתח petach
means the door is open.
door, it’s not just that it has to be unlocked, you actually
have to open it.
וילון מאי. Vilon mai. Now what about though if you’ve got a
curtain in the doorway? Is that mean that it’s sealed because you
don’t see the פתח, petach, you don’t actually see the, you know,
the opening, you know, or is it because there’s nothing that’s restricting
you, you just walk through? I mean you could say an unlocked
door you could just open, but there’s something about the unlocked door
that it’s a barrier, right, you know, you can’t just walk through,
you know, you’ll bang your head. Here you just walk through the
curtain and you’re there. So is that considered open or closed? Now
that’s a fascinating question because in the actual משכן, Mishkan, there wasn’t
a door. There was a curtain, right, you know, right, you know
how the משכן Mishkan right was? Right, you know, you had it,
right, you had like this and you had a curtain here, right?
So
actually, and that was considered פתח. petach. So of course this should
be considered פתח. petach. But maybe the point is like if the
whole thing is made, you know, I don’t know, like maybe it’s
like in a place where you have a serious structure and you
could put up a door, maybe you even have a door, right,
because I don’t think they’re restructuring the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But
let’s say they’re imagining that after you open the door, there’s then
a curtain after that door, you know, maybe one of those beads
things or whatever they are inside. So maybe in a context in
which you have a door and the or you could have a
door and there’s no door and there’s just a curtain, there maybe
the thinking is that the curtain, you know, should be considered, well
wait, if anything that’s more of a reason to say that it’s
considered open. Yeah, so it’s not clear to me why if it’s
considered open by the משכן, Mishkan, should there be a הוה אמינא
havah amina that a curtain should be considered closed by the בית
המקדש? Beit HaMikdash?
I’m not getting it. Is that what they say? Well, I’m saying
it, they’re not saying it. But I’m just saying what type of
crazy question is this about the curtain? The curtain is what they
had in the משכן, Mishkan, and that was considered פתח אהל מועד.
Petach Ohel Moed. Okay, I don’t know, maybe the point is that
the curtain didn’t totally seal the space because the way it sort
of operated, right, was sort of like, right, wasn’t it was,
you know, you could like walk around the curtain. Right, isn’t that
how it looked?
Maybe that’s the difference. It just doesn’t make sense to me as
if in the משכן Mishkan you’ve got a curtain
already and there clearly it’s considered opening.
Let’s get a picture of it.
No, the curtain goes all
the
way, darn it. Anyway, the curtain goes all the way across. So
even so, it was considered פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed. So
I’m really not getting what the, you know, I’m really not getting
what the point is, what the, hold on, let me see.
You see here, if you look at this picture, right?
See the picture? Right, the curtain goes all the way in front,
right, and it’s considered to be פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed.
So I don’t understand how we could think otherwise here.
Whatever, we’ve lost that historical context. So now let’s take a look.
I’m sure somebody has this question. So it says like this, okay,
so what’s the story with a curtain?
וילון מאי. Vilon mai. Where am I? And I lost my place.
I see. וילון מאי. Vilon mai. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira,
הוא הדין ונעשה כפתח. hu hadin venaaseh kepetach. What are you talking
about? A וילון, vilon, of course, is like an open door. I
don’t even understand what that means.
רש״י Rashi says אינו חשוב אלא כפתח. eino chashuv ela kepetach. Obviously
it’s open, it’s just there for modesty, it’s not there to keep
people out. You have a curtain so you’re it’s not visible what’s
going on, you know, it’s not openly visible to anybody at a
distance. So a curtain is there for modesty, it’s not there to
keep people out. A door is there to keep people out even
if you didn’t lock it, and therefore obviously a curtain is fine.
It’s still considered פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, which, as I
said, was just to me obvious from the case of the משכן.
Mishkan. All right, moving on. So a curtain is fine, a closed
door is not.
אלא כפתח פתוח. ela kepetach petuach. Okay, it itself is an open
doorway. גובה מאי. Govah mai. Now what if you’ve got some physical
obstruction in front of the door? Okay, now the funny thing is
that תוספות Tosafot says, aya, you got a physical obstruction in front
of the door. It’s known as the מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay, and if
you’re telling me that you can שחט shecht it here even with
the מזבח Mizbeach blocking, you know, your sight of the door, so
like what exactly is the הוה אמינא? havah amina? So it’s not
clear, תוספות Tosafot doesn’t really have a good answer. Maybe the question
is let’s say the obstruction was right up against the door, like
you had to climb over this obstruction, you know what I mean?
It wasn’t an actual door. If I had a mound of dirt
in front of my front door, my door is open, my door
is open, come anytime, except I got a mound of dirt, but
it’s not actually closing the door. All right, so anyway, the מזבח
Mizbeach is at least it blocks your visibility, but at least it
doesn’t block your access. Okay, so anyway, גובה מאי. Govah mai. What
about if there’s some obstruction there, some obstruction? on a mound of
dirt. תשמע דתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר שני פשפשין היו בבית
החליפות *Tashma datanya Rabi Yossi beribi Yehuda omer sheinei pishpeshin hayu beveit
hachalifot*. There were two like little doorways in the בית החליפות *Beit
Hachalifot*. And the בית החליפות *Beit Hachalifot* was this space, the אולם
ulam. *Ulam* here extended 15 אמות *amot* beyond the, you know, 15
אמות *amot* beyond the edge of the היכל heichal, *Heichal*, okay, and
this this is the אולם ulam *Ulam*. This is like the extra
hallway that was added in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* that wasn't
in the משכן *Mishkan*. And this area right here is like where
the כהנים *Kohanim* like there were there were holes in the wall
and they there was like their cubbies, their cubbies was like back
here by done by holes in the walls of the אולם ulam,
*Ulam*, and that was called the בית החליפות *Beit Hachalifot* where they
would like a חלף *chalaf* is a knife, that's where they would
put their knives in their various holes. Okay, so there what we're
going to say is, why is the place behind, right, the the
the door considered לפני אהל מועד *Lifnei Ohel Moed*, פתח אהל מועד
petach ohel moed. *Petach Ohel Moed*? And the answer is, cause there's
going to be a little doorway in the back of the בית
החליפות *Beit Hachalifot* on both sides. So when you're here, since in
theory you can go into this door, and through this door you
can get access into the into the אהל מועד *Ohel Moed*, that's
considered to be פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed. *Petach Ohel Moed*.
Now you have to admit it's a little funny, cause that's פתח
האולם *Petach HaUlam*, it's not פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed, *Petach
Ohel Moed*. The פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed. *Petach Ohel Moed*
is here, right, you're not still getting direct access to if you're
here in front of the opening of the אולם *Ulam* and you're
then, you know, wherever you are here, you're facing the also the
opening of the היכל *Heichal*, right, the opening of the היכל *Heichal*
is here, right? So you're also facing that. If you're behind the
the אולם *Ulam*, even if there's a little door, so even though
you can access it by going through the doors, you're not exactly
in front of the door, okay, but nevertheless, that's considered to be
sufficient and that's considered to make it that little door, to make
anything back here on a similar door they had on the other
side on the north side, so anything behind it was also considered
פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed? *Petach Ohel Moed*. Okay, so that
answers why why the sides are good. It says like this, שני
פשפשין
*sheinei pishpeshin*, two like little doors, היו בבית החליפות *hayu beveit hachalifot*,
וגובהן שמונה *vegovhan shmona*, they were eight אמות *amot* high, כדי להכשיר
את העזרה כולה לאכילת קדשי קדשים kodshei kodoshim ולשחיטת קדשים קלים *kedei
lehachshir et ha'azara kula leachilat kodshei kodashim ulishchitat kodashim kalim*. In order
to make the entire עזרה azarah *Azara* considered פתח אהל מועד petach
ohel moed. *Petach Ohel Moed*, to eat קדשי קדשים kodshei kodoshim, *kodshei
kodashim* and to shecht קדשים קלים *kodashim kalim*. Now, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to later take out eat קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* because
there was never a הלכה *halacha* that קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* had
to be eaten פתח אהל מועד *Petach Ohel Moed*. Yes, they can
be eaten in the whole עזרה azarah. *Azara*, that's what we've been
saying until now. תוכלו במקום קדוש *Tochlu bemakom kadosh*. But there was
never an idea of פתח אהל מועד *Petach Ohel Moed*, so you
didn't need a door to solve a problem. But for the שחיטה
*shechita*, the שחיטה *shechita* of קדשים קלים *kodashim kalim* is פתח אהל
מועד *Petach Ohel Moed*. So for that, you by having these doors
here, you made all this area behind also considered to be in
front of פתח אהל מועד *Petach Ohel Moed*. All right, מאי
לאו *mai lav*, to presumably eight means that the door was eight
אמות *amot* high, okay, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a bizarre
read of what the eight means. מאי לאו *mai lav*, does it
not when it says that these things are eight, mean מאי לאו
דאיכא קמייהו שמונה *mai
lav de'ika kamaihu shmona*, that in front of these doorways, these little
doorways at the back of the בית החליפות *Beit Hachalifot*, there was
some mound eight אמות *amot* high? This is completely bizarre, why would
I think there's a mound in the middle of the מקדש *Mikdash*?
It says the door was eight אמות *amot*, like it's such a
funny הוה אמינא *hava amina*. לא דגובהן נינהו שמונה *lo degavhan ninhu
shmona*. No, the door was eight אמות *amot* high, that's what it
means, not that there was a mound. So it's not relevant to
your question. מתיבי *meitivei*, one minute, how could you say the door
was eight אמות *amot*? This is what probably pushed the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* to have this strange read. כל השערים שהיו שם גובהן עשרים
אמה ורוחבן עשר אמה *Kol hashearim shehayu sham govhan esrim ama verochban
eser ama*. All the doors in the מקדש *Mikdash* were 20
אמות *amot* high and they were ten אמות *amot* wide. פשפשין שאני
*pishpeshin shani*. That's main doors, tiny little back doors are different. שמונה
*shmona* is still pretty big for a doorway. 16 feet, I've never
seen what doorway is 16 feet tall? You go to a castle
maybe. Anyway, or whatever, not even eight, even if you say an
אמה *ama* is a foot and a half, 12 feet, still pretty
high. And anyway, what's a standard door? Eight or something? Anyway, okay,
anyway,
מתיבי *meitivei*, so I'll ask you, כל השערים שהיו שם *kol hashearim
shehayu sham*, and we did that already, ואיכא צדדים *veika tsdadim*, so
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says one minute, I got a problem. It
says, this makes all of the space directly behind that 15 אמות
*amot* of protrusion פתח אהל מועד *Petach Ohel Moed*. What about the
stuff that's right at the edge here, you know, the southern edge
or right at the northern edge? So it is behind the opening
of the אולם *Ulam* and the היכל *Heichal* and it is off
to the side, it's not even facing, it's not in that
direct space in front of the what do you call it here.
Now you could still say you get it at an angle, great.
But what if it's not just down here at the southern edge,
what if it's the southern edge and it's behind it's right at
the width of the wall here from the from the front of
the אולם *Ulam* to the back of the אולם *Ulam*? So if
it's right here. here, right? Now you're really stuck, right? You're not
at all in front of either door, right? You're in that width
that's between the front door of the אולם and the back door
of the אולם. Like if you imagine a house. You got your
front door, your back door. Anywhere in the backyard, you're in front
of the back door. Anywhere in the front yard, you're in front
of the front door. But if you're off at the sides, you're
not in front of either door. Okay? So this is the front
door to your house, this is the back door. What about this?
That's not פתח אהל מועד. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what
do you do? So the גמרא Gemara. says,
דמיילי להו בקרן זוית. demayli lehu bekeren zavis. Okay. So you're right.
You don't put the door there. You put the door
at the corner. Here's the door to the—the back door to the
אולם was at the corner of the southern and the western wall.
And here a corner of the northern and the western wall. So
therefore, whether you're in the backyard or the side yard, the door
is a little bit facing you. Okay? And that allows this space
and this space. But now we're going to be left with: what
about this space? The space that's the backyard of the, you know,
as it were, right, of the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right? That
is not in front of either door. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אחורי בית הכפורת מאי? achorei beis hakappores mai? What about the space
behind where the ארון aron is? תא שמע, ta shema, דאמר אמי
בר יוד אמר רב, de'amar Ami bar Yud amar Rav, לול קטן
היה אחורי בית הכפורת. lul katan hayah achorei beis hakappores. There was
a tiny little opening like a window or a door maybe that
was at the back. גובהו שמונה אמות ורוחבו שמונה אמות govho shemoneh
amos verochvo shemoneh amos tall, כדי להכשיר את העזרה לאכילת קדשי קדשים
ולשחיטת קדשים קלים, kedai lehachshir es ha'azarah l'achilas kodshei kodoshim ul'shchitas kodoshim
kalim, to make anywhere in the עזרה azarah considered פתח אהל מועד.
So any form of access—again, there's got to be like a דרשה
drasha here, you know. Here it is, like it's all restricted access,
you know, the שכינה, shechinah, the כפורת, kappores, קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
you know, you have to go this way through the קדש, Kodesh,
אולם, היכל, דביר, dvir, whatever. But really the sense of like בכל
מקום אשר אזכיר את שמי אבוא אליך וברכתיך. bechol makom asher azkir
es shmi avo eilecha uverachticha. You know, anyway, God somehow will find
ways to make—get access. Anywhere you are, you're פתח אהל מועד, you
know, we'll make a back door here and a back door here
and so on.
Okay. Fine. Yes, the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim actually had a door
in the back? Well, it's more like a window. But it's a
big window. It's maybe it's an שמונה אמה shemoneh amah window or
something. I know, it is surprising. Yeah. So exactly, שמונה אמות shemoneh
amos is pretty darn big. Yeah, you would think that they
would—you know, you're actually right. Like I—it's a good point, I wasn't
stopping to think about it. But like what, you could actually peek
in and see the ארון? aron? Yeah, you're right, that is pretty
darn strange. I mean, and you could say it would be closed.
Well, maybe that's—go back to the גמרא. Maybe there would be a
וילון. vilon. If it was closed, then it wouldn't solve the problem.
So maybe there would be some curtain. Yeah, so I guess if
combining the things we said earlier, there's a way to make it
make sense. But yeah, it's a good point. Okay.
תוספות Tosafos asks the question. I mean, תוספות Tosafos says, ותימה דדרך
פשפשים לא היה יכול ליראות כלל. veseima de'derech pishpashim lo hayah yachol
lera'os klal. Well, anyway, whatever. No, he actually—that's a different question. Anyway,
so the גמרא says like this.
Okay, where are we? So it says like this, maybe it was
high up. But if it was high up off the ground, then
it would have answered our question about an obstruction too. Because like
what, you know, I don't know, she's got something that's a window
that if you get me a ladder I can climb through. I'm
not sure that counts as פתח אהל מועד. By calling it a
לול, lul, it's not clear if it was a window or a
door. And if it is a window, then that to some degree
doesn't even address the question we've been raising about what if there's
some form of obstruction. Okay, so let's anyway go back to see
the גמרא. The גמרא says,
okay, והיינו דכתיב שנים לפרבר. vehainu de'chsiv shenayim laparbar. Two guards for
the פרבר. parbar. מאי לפרבר? mai laparbar? אמר רבה בר רב שילא,
amar Rabbah bar Rav Shila, כמאן דאמר כלפי בר. keman de'amar klappei
bar. The stuff pointing to the back or outwards. So there were
two guards for this window in the back of the קדש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. Maybe exactly that, to keep people's eyes away. Okay. Anyway,
but what we have not done is we have not answered our
question about what's the story with an obstruction. Does that still consider
פתח אהל מועד? We'll read one more line so we begin the
next דף. daf. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, אין חייבין משום טומאה אלא על אורך מאה ושמונים ושבע ורוחב
מאה ושלושים וחמש. ein chayavin mishum tumah ela al orech me'ah ushmonim
v'shiva verochav me'ah ushloshim vachamesh. Okay. So now we're going to get
to this point about the actual עזרה. azarah All of our discussion
has been that the entire עזרה azarah is where you eat קדשי
קדשים and not where you—and where you can now שחט shacht because
we made everything פתח אהל מועד. It's where you can שחט shacht
קדשים קלים. Okay? And but the עזרה azarah includes the entire עזרה
azarah but not the עזרת נשים. ezras nashim. Okay? So as we've
been saying. So, right, so the עזרת נשים ezras nashim is going
to be here and the entire length of the עזרה Azara is,
what's the length?
187 by
135. 187 by 135. Okay. That's going to be the—and that's going
to be the עזרה proper, okay, and that's where you're
חייב chayav if you're טמא. tamei. So we will continue with that
tomorrow, discussing what makes the עזרה proper, where all the things get
done, קדשי קדשים, שחיטת קדשים קלים, shchitas kodshim kalim, חיוב טומאה chiyuv
tumah and so on, to be continued tomorrow.